The next argument form on our list is
something referred to as generalization.
And it is basically the idea that that
if I have some statement, I can always
take that statement or another
statement. If the original is true, then
that statement or something else is also
going to be true because an or statement
only needs one. So if I have any
statement P, I can generalize it to this
larger statement P or Q. So for example,
I said I'm a Canadian. that statement P
and I can therefore conclude that I am a
Canadian or I am a unicorn. One of those
two things must be true. And indeed
because I am a Canadian, the I am a
Canadian portion of the I am Canadian or
I am a unicorn part is true. And so this
this whole disjunction, this whole or
statement is going to be true. And this
says nothing about whether I am or am
not a unicorn. It doesn't matter. I only
need one of the two things. I've got the
Canadian part. That's all I need. Sort
of the opposite of generalization is
specialization.
If I have one statement and some other
statement. So in other words, I have I
have both of the statements true at the
same time. I might not care about both
of them equally. I have both of them,
but I don't need both of them. I only
care about one of them. I can just get
rid of the one I don't care about and
I'm left with just therefore say P. So,
for example, if I say I'm a Canadian and
I have a PhD, but my argument about uh
being the president of the United
States, it didn't matter whether I had a
PhD or not. That had nothing to do with
it. So, so while I have this statement,
I am Canadian and I have a PhD. I'm just
going to toss away the PhD portion of it
and just specialize down to the
statement I am Canadian, which is
needed. Now, both generalization and
specialization are both sort of quite
trivial and easy things. In fact, in
everyday language, we we use this all
the time, but we don't we don't use it
in the explicit structure that I'm
talking about here. However, when we're
trying to translate complicated long
arguments to mathematics, we want to
make sure that that every single step is
truly valid. And so, even for relatively
simple steps like the generalization or
the specialization, we want to make sure
that we know that this is true. We could
write down the truth tables for it if we
really wanted to. and therefore be
completely confident that I'm not making
any sort of mistake.
A final one, a very very important one
in mathematics, one that we're going to
be using a whole bunch is arguing by
contradiction.
And the idea is this. I'm trying to
prove a statement of P. What I do is I
assume I take as my conditional if not
P. I assume that that my statement is
actually false and I go along and I
derive some sort of contradiction or for
example a contradiction might be
something like zero is equal to one or
I'm a mammal and I am a reptile
something like this that just makes no
sense at all. So if assuming my
statement was false leads me to this
nonsensical contradiction, the
contradiction that's always false, then
my initial statement must indeed be
true. So this is the logical form of a
contradiction. Not P implies a
contradiction. Then my initial claim
must be true. And I'm actually going to
delay showing you an example of this
until a later